<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/">
<channel>
<title>Les Caves de Pyrene</title>
<atom:link href="https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<link>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk</link>
<description>Natural, organic, biodynamic, real wine and the people and places behind them</description>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 15:01:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
<language>en-GB</language>
<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.9</generator>
<item>
<title>All roads lead to Romorantin</title>
<link>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/12/16/all-roads-lead-to-romorantin/</link>
<comments>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/12/16/all-roads-lead-to-romorantin/#respond</comments>
<dc:creator>blog</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 15:01:51 +0000</pubDate>
<category>Uncategorized</category>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/?p=11634</guid>
<description>We have already tried to build an ark for forgotten grape varieties, and our list is still populated by examples of the rare and autochthonous. Sometimes they feature gloriously on their own – Gringet from Les Vins de Belema or Ribeyrenc Noir from Thierry Navarre, in other examples they will be part of a “blouge-y” [&amp;#8230;]</description>
<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;We have already tried to build an ark for forgotten grape varieties, and our list is still populated by examples of the rare and autochthonous. Sometimes they feature gloriously on their own – Gringet from Les Vins de Belema or Ribeyrenc Noir from Thierry Navarre, in other examples they will be part of a “blouge-y” field blend of mingled reds and whites such as Florent Plageoles Terroirists Printemps. When commercial imperatives push consumers towards the tried and tested – and the homogenous – it is wonderful to see producers reviving and replanting traditional varieties and giving us the opportunity to sample different flavours in wines.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;So, a big mention in dispatches for the Romorantin grape. Legend has it that Romorantin was introduced to the Loire by King Francis 1 (1494–1547). The commune of Romorantin-Lanthenay not far from the grape’s stronghold in Cheverny, suggesting that the grape’s name reflects a geographical connection – the king was from the region.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;DNA fingerprinting has shown that Romorantin is one of many grapes to be the result of a cross between Gouais Blanc and Pinot Fin Teinturier, making it a sibling of Chardonnay, amongst others.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;DNA fingerprinting has shown that Romorantin is one of many grapes to be the result of a cross between Gouais Blanc and Pinot Fin Teinturier, making it a sibling of Chardonnay, amongst others.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Romorantin is the designated grape for Cour-Cheverny appellation and around thirty producers work with it. Its reputation is being secured by natural wine growers who see its potential and are able to produce extraordinary wines from it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure id="attachment_9039" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-9039" style="width: 448px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=197DLd7W76t35ZwJ-_40iWnnlNBA-N-ZL"&gt;&lt;img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="wp-image-9039 size-full" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=197DLd7W76t35ZwJ-_40iWnnlNBA-N-ZL" alt="" width="448" height="299" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=197DLd7W76t35ZwJ-_40iWnnlNBA-N-ZL 448w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/Puzelat-small-300x200.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 448px) 100vw, 448px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption id="caption-attachment-9039" class="wp-caption-text"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thierry Puzelat&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The Puzelat family have worked with the grape for some time. Originally, it was as part of a joint project with Pierre-Olivier Bonhomme and a centenarian vineyard (planted on French rootstock). This wine was a veritable &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;vin de garde&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; and had an intensity that lingered remarkably on the palate. Aromas jostled for attention: lemon and chalk followed by mixed white fruits (white peaches, Mirabelle plums, pears), honey, almonds and clean, minerally scents reminiscent of finely-spun wool. It was complex on the palate, too, extremely vinous showing lemon-cream and honey. Ripe apple juiciness gave way to tart, steely acidity that sings like a taut violin string, providing balance and structure for the full, luscious fruit. On the second day the acidity became steelier and more penetrating, the flinty minerality more pronounced taking on back notes of ginger, white pepper, pear-skin and hell’s granny smiths…&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;More recent versions have been from younger vineyards planted to selection massale vines. From here, the wines are more fluid, expressing a bright chalky freshness. The latest vintage is almost a weightless 11%.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure id="attachment_11636" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-11636" style="width: 326px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1kXf9M3jTdHxR1VmFi_g9ngtRDyT1etgJ"&gt;&lt;img decoding="async" class="wp-image-11636 " src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1kXf9M3jTdHxR1VmFi_g9ngtRDyT1etgJ" alt="" width="326" height="509" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1kXf9M3jTdHxR1VmFi_g9ngtRDyT1etgJ 360w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Screenshot-2025-12-16-at-9.50.47-AM-192x300.png 192w" sizes="(max-width: 326px) 100vw, 326px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption id="caption-attachment-11636" class="wp-caption-text"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hervé Villemade &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Hervé Villemade, in Cour-Cheverny, makes two versions of Romorantin. We import “Les Acacias”, a wine characterised by its power and sheer intensity. Here the fleshy apricot fruit melds with a touch of oxidation and creates a multi-layered wine with liquorice bitters, warm ginger and fine tannins. The grapes are from vines average 50+-year-old and the wine is half-fermented in amphora and half in demi-muid before ageing in same vessels for 14 months with a further 10 months thereafter in bottle.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;“Nature admits no lie”, as Carlyle said, and Courtois (Claude) often says that his wine is made from “true grapes.” The wines he and Etienne craft are pure and vibrantly alive, testament to outstanding farming and precise winemaking. Claude, as we know, is one of the wild men of the region, fierce, generous and capricious, guiding beautiful, naturally expressive wines to the bottle. There is something about Romorantin with almost sherry aromas of oxidation and this example grows in the glass as if eating the oxygen that should be destroying it. The texture evolves into lanolin; warmth pervades the mouth. It is like nothing you have ever tasted, and one imagines that every time one tries the wine it will be a different experience.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=12SX8kNoreY4oWQG2WtEWnLWlQzwCUcK2"&gt;&lt;img decoding="async" class="wp-image-11637 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=12SX8kNoreY4oWQG2WtEWnLWlQzwCUcK2" alt="" width="476" height="346" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=12SX8kNoreY4oWQG2WtEWnLWlQzwCUcK2 982w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Screenshot-2025-12-16-at-9.34.14-AM-300x218.png 300w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Screenshot-2025-12-16-at-9.34.14-AM-768x558.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 476px) 100vw, 476px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;2024 Romorantin Frileuse, Clos du Tue-Boeuf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1Vmh5eMaL5F7A0xA9wRyzlh3agYiucrYD"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-11638 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1Vmh5eMaL5F7A0xA9wRyzlh3agYiucrYD" alt="" width="392" height="320" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1Vmh5eMaL5F7A0xA9wRyzlh3agYiucrYD 1012w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Screenshot-2025-12-16-at-9.35.39-AM-300x245.png 300w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Screenshot-2025-12-16-at-9.35.39-AM-768x627.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 392px) 100vw, 392px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;2022 Cour-Cheverny “Les Acacias”, Hervé Villemade&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1IIaOaz1CtUNCJQSYlyp_dY4iPc0vt9fs"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-10668 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1IIaOaz1CtUNCJQSYlyp_dY4iPc0vt9fs" alt="" width="228" height="569" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1IIaOaz1CtUNCJQSYlyp_dY4iPc0vt9fs 420w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Cailloux-du-Paradis-Romorantin-2019-120x300.jpg 120w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Cailloux-du-Paradis-Romorantin-2019-410x1024.jpg 410w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 228px) 100vw, 228px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;2023 Romorantin, Les Cailloux du Paradis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interested in finding more about the Romorantin wines mentioned? Contact us directly:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:shop@lescaves.co.uk"&gt;shop@lescaves.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; |  &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:sales@lescaves.co.uk"&gt;sales@lescaves.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; | 01483 538820&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
<wfw:commentRss>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/12/16/all-roads-lead-to-romorantin/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
</item>
<item>
<title>Wine Trade Gobbledegook: busting industry jargon</title>
<link>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/12/15/wine-trade-gobbledegook-busting-industry-jargon/</link>
<comments>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/12/15/wine-trade-gobbledegook-busting-industry-jargon/#respond</comments>
<dc:creator>blog</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 15:46:06 +0000</pubDate>
<category>Uncategorized</category>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/?p=11631</guid>
<description>The trouble with jargon is that it is catching. We consciously (or unconsciously) echo this slanguage as if using certain hackneyed words or expressions is the only way to grab people’s attention and to allow us to speak with apparent authority on a particular issue. The wine trade rejoices in its own gobbledegook, an unironic [&amp;#8230;]</description>
<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1SXBFZ6MTmg41tFn48481_hPELRhvN6xA"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-11632 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1SXBFZ6MTmg41tFn48481_hPELRhvN6xA" alt="" width="643" height="643" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1SXBFZ6MTmg41tFn48481_hPELRhvN6xA 810w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Blue-Orange-Word-Search-Word-Find-Instagram-Post-300x300.png 300w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Blue-Orange-Word-Search-Word-Find-Instagram-Post-150x150.png 150w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Blue-Orange-Word-Search-Word-Find-Instagram-Post-768x768.png 768w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Blue-Orange-Word-Search-Word-Find-Instagram-Post-600x600.png 600w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 643px) 100vw, 643px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The trouble with jargon is that it is catching. We consciously (or unconsciously) echo this &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;slanguage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; as if using certain hackneyed words or expressions is the only way to grab people’s attention and to allow us to speak with apparent authority on a particular issue.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The wine trade rejoices in its own gobbledegook, an unironic buzzword-ridden lexicon of banality that seems to proclaim by virtue of its very usage that the wine industry is hard-wired into professional practice. If it quacks like a professional, it must be a professional.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Let’s bust some jargon. God forbid that we ever think that wine is a beautiful beverage made from hand-plucked grapes grown in an idyllic vineyard and that we are the storytellers as well as the sellers of the product. There is too much emphasis on magic marketing, of each and every wine being seen as a brand that needs to be packaged in a particular way and sold to expectation.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The wine trade rejoices in its own gobbledegook, an unironic buzzword-ridden lexicon of banality that seems to proclaim by virtue of its very usage that the wine industry is hard-wired into professional practice. If it quacks like a professional, it must be a professional.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Probably, my favourite hate-word is &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;premiumisation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;. It’s the -isation that sends me over the edge. It is the art/science of persuading people to spend more money on a bottle of wine by making that wine an aspirational product (another pet hate term). You want consumers to examine their choices, recognise extra quality, and consequently voluntarily choose to go up a rung on the wine spend ladder.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Segmentation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; in business is the process of dividing a broad market into smaller, more specific groups of customers based on shared characteristics like demographics, needs, or behaviours. This allows companies to create more effective marketing, product development, and sales strategies by tailoring their efforts to the unique preferences of each segment. Treating people like they are individuals? Whatever next? Marketing treats individuals as consumer units, views behaviour via algorithms. Surely, the wine is the wine is the wine, and the human being is a bundle of complex impulses, thoughts and feelings. I don’t want to wake up every day feeling as if  I am a mere &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;segment&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Strategies&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;. Wine and PR companies constantly have meetings to explore their strategic options with the purpose of finding ways and means of obtaining greater recognition for  &amp;#8211; and selling – (more) products. The more one agonises about strategy, the further away one is from the wines themselves and the people who choose wine on its merits.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;SKU&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; – Pronounced skew. Eww! Short for stock keeping unit, a unique, alphanumeric code assigned by a company to a specific product for internal inventory management. These are wines, not numbers. “I am not a number, I am a free man!” shouted Patrick McGoohan at the beginning of each episode of The Prisoner. Wines are not numbers, not names evening, but compressed histories.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Brand (brand recognition)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; – It is almost impossible not to use the b word in everyday wine conversation. We do all in our power to dissociate ourselves from the term, yet without doubt, larger and more famous estates become de facto brands by virtue of their reputation. A branded product is normally a consistent one – certainly at the cheaper end, where supermarket shelves are largely populated by wines from companies that churn out the same labels, the same wines, year upon year.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;God forbid that we ever think that wine is a beautiful beverage made from hand-plucked grapes grown in an idyllic vineyard and that we are the storytellers as well as the sellers of the product.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Boutique &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;derives from the word for a small (usually specialist) shop, but has come to mean fashionable, exclusive and niche. In wine parlance, it might refer to a small-production wine made by artisan methods. In reality, boutique wines seem to mean &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;any&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; cuvees that are made at a higher-end price point  and in lower quantities.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Launch,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;initiative&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; – A marketing idea. Many initiatives involve giving pr companies money to plant stories in as many trade journals as possible to launch the product in question. In that sense, a product is launched when journalists/trade magazines give it the oxygen of publicity. The brand money is talking, but who is listening? High volume, relentless exposure surely does have an effect in terms of building recognition for a brand, but in the professional world of wine, any wine cannot rest on its laurels. It needs to be tasted, assessed – not just by journalists – but the very individuals who are in a position to buy it and sell it on. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Jargon is used in a more tongue-in-cheek way in the natural wine sphere. We talk of unicorns (wines so unobtainable that they have an almost mythic status) and bangers (wines that are very good indeed). We also use a lot of flip terms as shorthand for complex concepts. Language doesn’t have to be precise when talking about wine, particularly one’s personal impressions. One should call out the prevalence of frankly ugly terminology that depersonalises wine and treats it as a functional business product. Especially when that wine is a living product and a soulful thing and gives rise to moments of deep appreciation and pleasure.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Stay in the loop and never miss a tasting or jargon-free newsletter! Contact us to request to be added to our mailing list:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;shop@lescaves.co.uk&lt;/strong&gt; |  &lt;strong&gt;sales@lescaves.co.uk&lt;/strong&gt; | 01483 538820&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
<wfw:commentRss>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/12/15/wine-trade-gobbledegook-busting-industry-jargon/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
</item>
<item>
<title>Are You a Wine Nerd? Take Our Quiz!</title>
<link>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/12/08/are-you-a-wine-nerd-take-our-quiz/</link>
<comments>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/12/08/are-you-a-wine-nerd-take-our-quiz/#respond</comments>
<dc:creator>blog</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 15:49:07 +0000</pubDate>
<category>Uncategorized</category>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/?p=11622</guid>
<description>In the Doctor Who episode &amp;#8220;Robot of Sherwood,&amp;#8221; the Doctor angrily declares: &amp;#8220;That isn&amp;#8217;t even funny. That was bantering. I am totally against bantering.”  Wine has come a long way since the hushed recommendations in gentlemen’s clubs, arcane classification systems and equally arcane terminology. Over the past forty years wine has been demystified for new generations [&amp;#8230;]</description>
<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1aIXvBAG9pAXmxJa_wVobVEQzYSuAg0bF"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-11623 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1aIXvBAG9pAXmxJa_wVobVEQzYSuAg0bF" alt="" width="294" height="588" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1aIXvBAG9pAXmxJa_wVobVEQzYSuAg0bF 640w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/cartoon-1300661_1280-150x300.png 150w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/cartoon-1300661_1280-512x1024.png 512w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 294px) 100vw, 294px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;In the Doctor Who episode &amp;#8220;Robot of Sherwood,&amp;#8221; the Doctor angrily declares: &amp;#8220;That isn&amp;#8217;t even funny. That was bantering. I am totally against bantering.”  Wine has come a long way since the hushed recommendations in gentlemen’s clubs, arcane classification systems and equally arcane terminology. Over the past forty years wine has been demystified for new generations of drinkers in various ways and the fact younger drinkers feel confident enough to banter about a subject once considered the sole parole of the middle-aged upper middle class “elite” shows how relaxed we have become about wine.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;New tropes still replace old ones, snobbery becomes reverse snobbery, and the language and rituals surrounding wine constantly changes. Plus ça change.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;It’s easy to pretend we are above “all that”, but (whether knowingly or otherwise) we do say and do things about and around wine that mark us as playing the wine bantz game.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Wine has come a long way since the hushed recommendations in gentlemen’s clubs, arcane classification systems and equally arcane terminology.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The important rule here is to be truthful. Of course, no-one wants to be stereotyped as Nerd of Nerd Hall, a walking decanter full of wine cliches, and we acknowledge that it is nigh impossible, when gathered together with a group of fellow wine-lovers, not to fall victim to clubby wine banter. This quiz, however, is designed (if that is not too much of an exaggeration) to see whether you might be in danger of tipping over into the self-parodic wine lover extraordinaire or whether you still possess a modicum of detachment. Reverse bonus points are available (see questions underneath the main quiz) to mitigate against pretension.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1v3QzWjRcfMQ5iMd_LsPKlaeyWYW-vyx_"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-11624 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1v3QzWjRcfMQ5iMd_LsPKlaeyWYW-vyx_" alt="" width="574" height="287" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1v3QzWjRcfMQ5iMd_LsPKlaeyWYW-vyx_ 1280w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/quiz-2058883_1280-300x150.png 300w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/quiz-2058883_1280-1024x512.png 1024w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/quiz-2058883_1280-768x384.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 574px) 100vw, 574px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Wine Bantz Quiz&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li style="list-style-type: none;"&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you are a member of a wine group that meets three or more times a year to show off fancy wines – 20 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Add extra 5 points&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; if the majority of wines brought to these meetings are from Burgundy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Add extra 10 points&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; if the majority of the wines brought to these meetings are from Jura &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li style="list-style-type: none;"&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you will never order a wine below £60 in a restaurant as a matter of principle – 5 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have ever engaged in the game of Vintagemanship:  saying for example: “ this is a perfectly okay version of that wine, but have you tried x/y/z vintage…” – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have ever said with enthusiastic emphasis: “This is the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;best ever&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;…” about any aspect of a wine – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Following on from these, if you have ever deliberately brought into conversation with fellow drinkers the fact that you have tried several vintages of a particular famous wine – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;5 additional marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; if you referred to it as a “vertical”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have ever used the expression “wine unicorn” or “iconic producer” – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have said that a new grape variety or region is trending or predicted the next big thing in wine – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you say that you never read critics or remember their scores, yet you have a subscription to Purple Pages and an encyclopaedic knowledge of Wine Advocate 100 point icons – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have ever ordered one last bottle of wine at the end of the evening in a restaurant that you really wanted to try – were very disappointed &amp;#8211; and wished you hadn’t? – 1o marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have bought a copy of every Noble Rot magazine since it was first published – 20 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have ever said that the wine is “sick” in a gratuitously bantzy way – 20 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have more than one or more meaningful conversations in a year about wine glassware and are extremely snobby about what you drink out of at home – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you are a bore about growers’ champagne (because you can name more than half a dozen small growers) – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;10 extra marks if you have spotted a wine from a small champagne grower and exclaimed out loud: “Oh, they have so-and-so on the list!”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;5 further marks if your exclamation can clearly be heard on the next table.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;10 more marks if you have drunk Selosse in the last three years and refuse to shut up about it in polite wine company.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have been to Paris, and drunk a cuvee of natural wine that is made specifically for a certain wine bar (and that makes it obviously better &amp;#8211; in your opinion &amp;#8211; than all the other wine that grower makes) – 20 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have ever remarked that a certain single de-alcoholised wine is surprisingly good (in order that you don’t seem like a wine snob) – 5 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have ever pretended to be utterly familiar with a grape variety that is almost extinct or so rare that there are only a tiny handful of extant examples that hardly anyone has ever tasted – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have ever corrected someone who is talking about hybrid grapes and mentioned that they are PiWis – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you actually even know what PiWi stands for – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have boasted amongst wine friends of having visited the cellar or the vineyard of the iconic producer that you are drinking at that precise moment – 20 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you refer to a famous producer by their first name, diminutive or nickname. – 20 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you understand the wax colour code pertaining to the Overnoy Jura wines – 20 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you refuse to say Poulsard (even it is written that way on the label) and refer to a wine as Ploussard. – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have ever liked a particularly stupid or unfunny wine meme (be honest!) on Instagram – 5 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have ever written down five or more adjectives to describe the colour of a wine in a tasting. – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have ever added a massive pinch of whimsy to jazz up a tasting note (for example, an exceedingly far-fetched simile or metaphor). – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you ever used the expression: “I (once) went to a masterclass on… given by…” or similar to authenticate your wine nerd credentials in company – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you ever deliberately tried to catch out a sommelier or wine waiter in a restaurant by asking a question on wine that is impossible for them to know the answer – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you ever gone into a wine shop and ask for a wine you already know they don’t have – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you deliberately cod-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;anglicise&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; the pronunciation of French wine terms in a clunky way to show that you are above wine snobbery.  – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you deliberately over-emphasise your French pronunciation of wine terms, by affectedly rolling your rs as if you have been suddenly possessed by a language demon – 20 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you turn your nose up at (or refuse to buy) negoce wines made by a famous grower – 20 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have ever uttered the sentiment that “Garnacha is the Pinot Noir of Spain” (or that any grape variety is the new Pinot Noir etc.) – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have ever pretended (to yourself or to others) a wine is better than it is – because of its unicorn/iconic reputation alone. – 20 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If your profound love of Barolo and Barbaresco is based on the fact that they are such difficult to appreciate when they are young and others are unable to understand the glories of the Nebbiolo grape– 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have ever said that English sparkling wines are as good, if not better, than champagne. And meant it. – 15 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you call regenerative farming “regen” for short. – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have ever patiently explained the difference/similarity between Pinot Grigio and Pinot Gris to someone who doesn’t know about wine – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Remove&lt;/b&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; points to the value of below if any of the following apply to you.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have ever put a bottle of cru classé Bordeaux in the freezer to give it an edge &amp;#8211; &amp;#8211; 30 marks (+10 more if first growth)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you won’t order a bottle of wine above £60 in a restaurant – as a matter of principle – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you shake up a bottle of Col Fondo Prosecco before serving it – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have an expensive corkscrew, but you only use a cheap shitty one – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If -when pouring – you have ever missed the wine glass completely – 5 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If when opening a bottle of champagne you ever have broken anything with a flying cork, or injured someone, or yourself. – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have ever ordered a wine by the vintage alone (thinking it was the bin number) – 20 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have ever ordered the house retsina in a Greek restaurant &amp;#8212; 20 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;And enjoyed it – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you generally prefer Gewurztraminer to Riesling – 20 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have ever sent back a bottle of wine because it is too sulphury – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have ever put an ice cube in a glass of white Burgundy to chill it down. – 10 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you have ordered a white wine spritzer in the last year – 20 marks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1pVWpM1_oAIEYalfoFzSYAXRIiWTfxjVY"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-11625 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1pVWpM1_oAIEYalfoFzSYAXRIiWTfxjVY" alt="" width="357" height="357" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1pVWpM1_oAIEYalfoFzSYAXRIiWTfxjVY 1280w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/icon-6065420_1280-300x300.png 300w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/icon-6065420_1280-1024x1024.png 1024w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/icon-6065420_1280-150x150.png 150w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/icon-6065420_1280-768x768.png 768w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/icon-6065420_1280-600x600.png 600w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 357px) 100vw, 357px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;What’s Your WNQ Total – (Wine Nerd Quotient)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Below 50 – Spritzer &amp;amp; house Rioja (not in the same glass)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;51-99 – Pinot Gris is the new Pinot Grigio&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;100-149 – Red wine served at room temperature&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;150 &amp;#8211; 199 – Drinking Assyrtiko in Santorini as the sun sets&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;200-249 – Annual subscription to Noble Rot magazine&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;250-299– Artisan Blanc de Blancs Champagne only&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;300- 349 &amp;#8211; The latest obscure small biodynamic Burgundy producer &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;350-399 –Successful ascent to the summit of Mont Vin Jaune in Nerdistan&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;400+ &amp;#8211; Wine is my entire &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;raisin d’etre&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
<wfw:commentRss>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/12/08/are-you-a-wine-nerd-take-our-quiz/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
</item>
<item>
<title>Three Decades in the Wine Trade</title>
<link>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/12/05/three-decades-in-the-wine-trade/</link>
<comments>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/12/05/three-decades-in-the-wine-trade/#respond</comments>
<dc:creator>blog</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 16:43:18 +0000</pubDate>
<category>Uncategorized</category>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/?p=11617</guid>
<description>It just struck me. Next year, I will have worked 30 years for one company. The days of wine. Laughs, we had a few.  Allow me to clamber creakily into my rocking chair by the fire, while I reminisce in quavery tones about the good old days. &amp;#160; Some of the changes I have witnessed [&amp;#8230;]</description>
<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;It just struck me. Next year, I will have worked 30 years for one company. The days of wine. Laughs, we had a few.  Allow me to clamber creakily into my rocking chair by the fire, while I reminisce in quavery tones about the good old days.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Some of the changes I have witnessed in our business over the years have been commercially-driven, others the result of cultural shifts. Resist the urge to use the word paradigm. The way we sell, talk about, even drink, wine has changed considerably, as it will always change, with the emergence of new generations of drinkers. Currently, the wine trade is agonising (for which read &amp;#8216;beating itself up&amp;#8217;) about the preferences of Generation Z, how to capture the hearts, minds, and above all, the purchasing power, of the next age of young consumers. Grouping whole generations into these preference categories is exactly the pointless activity that gives us wine trade folk unnecessary heebie-jeebies. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1NxxA_maufvL0AS282wmq9eVcr2i-f-qb"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-11618 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1NxxA_maufvL0AS282wmq9eVcr2i-f-qb" alt="" width="437" height="554" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Many of my unreliable memories about life in the trade are recounted in &lt;a href="https://www.the-buyer.net/opinion/doug-wreggs-history-of-les-caves-de-pyrene-in-10-1-2-chapters" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;A History of an Unusual Wine Company in 10 ½ Chapters,&lt;/a&gt; a biography recounting the progress of a small caterpillar group of naïve/intrepid wine sellers becoming a more professional butterfly company that ultimately reached (one way or another) a worldwide audience whilst managing to retain its ideals and much of its original identity. In the sense that whenever we tried something different, trade people would roll their eyes and utter comments such as: “that’s such a Les Caves de Pyrene thing to do!” As well as being a celebration of our sheer existence, the book related various instances of being original, taking risks and sticking to principles. It recounted examples of where success was arguably down to believing in what you were doing (and enjoying the ride). Inasmuch as there was a moral to the book, it was that fond ideas can become reality if you work hard enough to make it happen. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;When I joined Les Caves de P, we numbered four bodies in total. With a battered van and unknown wines matched by our unknown reputation, we were propelled by some strange romantic love of wines of south west France and the Languedoc. It was like supporting a team in the lower reaches of one of football’s nether leagues. You felt that others admired your devotion to a lost cause but would never take you seriously as a vendor of wines.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If this sounds suspiciously like the pious nostrums spouted in self-help books, believe me that luck, serendipity and naïve stubbornness certainly played a part in getting to where we are today.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;As personnel were replaced over time, the nature of the company was also bound to change. Somehow, we became bigger. Relatively secure and successful. The days of trampled shoe leather and ear fleas are a distant memory, although a scant few of us can still remember what it was like to be on our uppers.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;When I joined Les Caves de P, we numbered four bodies in total. Most of the business came out of our small shop in Guildford. We hawked wines to a handful of local Surrey bistros plus a few French restaurants in London. With a battered van and unknown wines matched by our unknown reputation, we were propelled by some strange romantic love of wines of south west France and the Languedoc. It was like supporting a team in the lower reaches of one of football’s nether leagues. You felt that others admired your devotion to a lost cause but would never take you seriously as a vendor of wines.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Autres temps, autres mœurs.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Without publicity or notoriety in the trade, leads were few and far between.  And without the internet, no-one could “look us up” and see what we were about. We were thus ploughing a very lonely furrow.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure id="attachment_5965" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-5965" style="width: 851px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1M3pvMHHn8W9iD34eL1TXsNIb_kaEJU81"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-5965" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1M3pvMHHn8W9iD34eL1TXsNIb_kaEJU81" alt="" width="851" height="568" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1M3pvMHHn8W9iD34eL1TXsNIb_kaEJU81 1750w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/lescaves6-300x200.jpg 300w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/lescaves6-768x512.jpg 768w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/lescaves6-1024x683.jpg 1024w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 851px) 100vw, 851px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption id="caption-attachment-5965" class="wp-caption-text"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Les Cave de Pyrene&amp;#8217;s original name was Santat Wines&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Of course, wine information in general was equally hard to come by. Classic books were our oracles. Jancis Robinson listed her noble grape varieties in Wines, Vines &amp;amp; Grape Varieties. Hugh Johnson, Michael Broadbent, Serena Sutcliffe, Steven Spurrier and Oz Clarke were heavyweights of the wine lit scene. Wine courses taught received wine wisdom. all about the classic regions and varieties. We were at best the obscure row of Aligoté next to a grand cru vineyard. (Okay this is out-of-date – we all prize Aligoté now!). Our artillery, such as it was, was confined to smart-value vin de pays from southern France and some Gascon appellation wines. Was the wine world clamouring for these wines? Was it heck.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;To sell wine, one had to be thick-skinned and persistent. The cold-often frigid-call was the only means of contacting a prospect. Effectively this rocking up on someone’s doorstep with a polite smile, proffering a wine catalogue with a business card, was like shouting into a hurricane. Occasionally, you might leave an open bottle in the hope that it would be sampled and be the siren song for its virtues, prompting an instant desire to list it. However, if a restaurateur or sommelier didn’t want you hanging around, you left. In other words, don’t call us, we’ll call you!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The other, and perhaps more effective, method was to network like crazy. Attend any and every tasting, party or dinner regardless of merit, eat the rubber chicken, and pump people for information in the nicest possible way. Social milieus were neutral territory. Outside the adversarial buyer/seller context, you were able to be yourself as well as use these moments of brief camaraderie to acquire information. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Discovering who to sell to was tricky enough, let alone ascertain the names of responsible buyers at each establishment. There was no Instagram or Linked In to look up which would might you to piece together the relevant information. Our reference points were invariably The Good Food Guide, Egon Ronay, Time Out Restaurant Guide and Harden’s. And gossiping with fellow trade members. Nowadays, one can open a restaurant or retail web page, look at the wine list and decide whether the target is suitable, and if so, how to approach it and whom you should talk to. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If you weren’t traipsing in off the street on the off chance, contacting potential customers had to be done using a landline. So quaint! In which case, one had to navigate the gatekeepers of the switchboard or a stern manager who would evaluate whether your call was either useful or desirable.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;mirabile dictu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;, you managed to snag your customer-victim and sell them some wine, then conveying information and keeping them au courant was not a cinch. In the 1990s, we were still sending letters and faxing (thanks to Alexander Bain – not the grower in Pouilly-Fumé!) and Giovanni Castelli for that little invention).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;E-mailing is the natural order of the day now, although we have customers who hardly ever respond even on this simple medium and require texting, Whats-Apping, or Insta-messaging to elicit any response.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;To sell wine, one had to be thick-skinned and persistent. The cold-often frigid-call was the only means of contacting a prospect. Effectively this rocking up on someone’s doorstep with a polite smile, proffering a wine catalogue with a business card was like shouting into a hurricane. Occasionally, you might leave an open bottle in the hope that it would be sampled and be the siren song for its virtues, prompting an instant desire to list it. However, if a restaurateur or sommelier didn’t want you hanging around, you left. In other words, don’t call us, we’ll call you!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Contacts are easier to come by these days. With history under our belts and somewhat of a reputation, potential customers will contact us. To convert speculative interest into a living, breathing, interesting account requires diligent nurturing, the best of sales craft.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The wine scene has altered dramatically in thirty years. Whereas once a few merchants operated in the wine trade,  now there are a few hundred. And whereas once a wine buyer in an establishment would have a relationship with the owner of a company, now buying is mediated through wine reps, sales desks, credit control, and automated ordering. Efficiency is prized as much as quality. In a frenzied competitive market, sales reps in wine companies are running around more and more chasing business, because they are worried that they will lose customers to competitors who will put together better offers. As the Red Queen says in Alice in Wonderland: “Here we must run as fast as we can, just to stay in place.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;And money is key.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;On one level of business, wine lists are no longer about wine and are instead simple revenue-raising commodity brochures. Now, you have to formulate proposals for inspection in order to be nominated to supply a group. This will involve form-filling, contracts, incentives, targets, and in many cases, financial rewards. Money has never talked louder than it does at this moment, and major wine companies will need to use brand support to clinch these big one or two year contracts. This bidding for business has an inflationary effect. Big restaurant groups are demanding hundreds and thousands of pounds for sole supply. Big wine companies are acceding to these demands. Wine policy is increasingly dictated by accountants and shareholders. The biggest deal is usually seen as the best deal. Wine is just a by-product in these cases. Large wine companies are effectively buying business turnover.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Although the above disadvantages smaller companies, they don’t have to worry about losing business to the next big bidder that comes along.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Arguably, the two most common words in the wine world are gross and profit (GP for short). Remember the days of 66.7% gross profit margins? Pepperidge Farm remembers. I can remember further back than that! When you could easily populate a list with exceptional wines under £30. When cash margins were as much the rule as the exception. When the bean counter mentality did not dominate discourse and actions. Glass price ceilings were made to be broken, but price rises on wine lists have been exponential rather than gradual. With some virtuous exceptions, there are few establishments that don’t adhere rigorously to high margins (which so penalises the adventurous drinker). With the cost of wine increasing year on year, the value of wine in restaurants has gone down and down, making it an almost luxury commodity for diners.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;On a more positive note, wine service overall has changed for the better. As a former sommelier, I have never been a fan of often intimidating, overly-formal wine service. Somms are usually younger, more engaging, more travelled, more open-minded, more willing to listen and communicate. There are now so many more women in the wine trade. And younger people too.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure id="attachment_5794" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-5794" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1xRXFCBWgLSjgPjpZRpVujqb0aZkum2s_"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-5794" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1xRXFCBWgLSjgPjpZRpVujqb0aZkum2s_" alt="" width="650" height="476" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1xRXFCBWgLSjgPjpZRpVujqb0aZkum2s_ 650w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/unnamed-300x220.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption id="caption-attachment-5794" class="wp-caption-text"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Les Caves (formerly Santat) original shop front&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Here are some of the other changes that have occurred over the past thirty years. In no particular order:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The irresistible rise of organic wines, biodynamic wines and natural wines. Even twenty-five years ago, the concept of an organic wine was unusual, biodynamic farming was considered a voodoo science practised purely by eccentrics, and the natural wine scene did not exist at all. Scroll on a quarter of a century…&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The proliferation of the wine (and other gastronomic) fairs and ancillary events (such as wine conferences). Is all the hoop-la sustainable? No, but deemed necessary, in the sense of if there is one thing worse than being talked about, that is not being talked about. Even if a winemaker has no wine to sell, they will still attend a fair to be part of the general conversation.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The disappearance of the national newspaper wine column. Pepperidge Farm remembers the great wine columnists who would craft beautiful discursive prose. Editors now give their wine writers very short shrift, and the columns have dwindled into brief pieces padded with supermarket wine of the month recommendations. The better wine columns and information sites have disappeared behind paywalls and are aimed at professionals. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The growth of the monetisation of wine and advertorial writing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Social media replacing the authoritative wine expert as a means of communicating about wine. Viral word of mouth, the picture and meme painting a thousand words.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The demystification of wine through wine courses.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The proliferation of podcasts. Guilty as charged! The success of this format is down to the busy lives we lead. There are two types of podcasts: one is polished to a fault, cleverly edited, and designed to stand the test of wine. The mission here is to inform. The other is a rough cut with likeminded people rapping about whatever topic moves them. #justanotherwinepodcast is in the latter mould, mixing information and opinion in equal measure.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The proliferation of jargon when describing wine. My bête-noire is a tasting note that sounds like a cross between a regurgitated thesaurus and the fruits being proffered at Goblin Market.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Moving away from new oak maturation in certain regions to reflect changing taste in markets around the world. One of my wine mentors used to describe certain wines as tasting like under-wined oak. These wines are still being made, but are they still being drunk?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The word “terroir” deployed willy-nilly. Although the expression has been used since the 15&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;th&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; century, it has become a marketing tool for a lot of producers who make distinctly un-terroir-like wines!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The growth of wine tourism. Travel is so easy, that so many regions are accessible. Wineries have set themselves up to receive visitors and do cellar door sales (good for margins).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Appellation becoming irrelevant. Partly because so many appellations have been devalued by the oppressive bureaucracy that runs them, often driving the best and most innovative producers to leave the system.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Wine lists are still being &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;curated&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;. This reminds me of the 11&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;th&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; doctor saying: I could be a curator. I&amp;#8217;d be great at curating, I&amp;#8217;d be &amp;#8220;The Great Curator.&amp;#8221; I have a feeling this pompous word  &amp;#8211; used in conjunction with wine lists &amp;#8211; originated in the US and is much beloved by PR companies to suggest a grand artistic endeavour. In short, it means putting together a bunch of wines you like from your favourite suppliers. Assembling a balanced list of good value wines involves knowledge and common sense – neither rocket science or artistic credentials.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Wine being treated as booze/alcohol by a succession of governments, as a cash cow, a commodity to be taxed.  I admit, I am pro wine. It is not just any drink. Wine has formed a part of culture and civilisation for thousands of years. Governments see all alcohol as the enemy. This is cultural philistinism meets joyless Presbyterianism wrapped up in something or other!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Trends… &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Yakety yak English wine. This is, of course, now a thing. The real proof will be to taste whether the country’s still wines progress over the next few years (with vineyards experiencing the positive effects of climate change &amp;#8211; big if). Commercial interest in English wine has increased greatly and this has manifested in an aggressive PR campaign. However, the still wines are relatively overpriced, and the quality rarely matches what you might buy from various other countries.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Georgia (and her wine) have been discovered –the darling of the left-field wine enthusiast. Wine pilgrims beat a reverential path to Georgia to rediscover their love of wine culture. Georgia reciprocates, welcoming them with open arms, endless feasts, and plenty of incapacitating chacha.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;On the wane – the regard for Californian and Australian wines in the UK. This is not a scientific observation, but, whether it is price or carbon footprint or ineffectual pr or simply a desire from restaurant and retail buyers to major in European wines, these particular countries are not as apparently popular as they once were. To be fair, the UK market is probably not very important to Californian producers and the wine industry, and Australian wines are still very much part of our wine culture, albeit less dominant than they used to be in their 80s and 90s heydays.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Growth in rosé and white wine drinking at the expense of red wine. We can thank a mixture of climate change, the new generation of wine consumers who prefer lighter and brighter wines, and the middle class embracing a more Mediterranean diet and wanting wines to match. Wine is no longer only encountered in posh restaurants; it is drunk in pubs and bars, drunk in parks, viewed as a refreshing drink, something to relax around and socialise with. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Orange/skin contact wine! – Georgian wines, Gravner, Radikon and the Friuli gang may have started the orange bang, but their influence has spread to winemakers throughout the world. The popularity of these wines (sometimes referred to as the fourth colour of wine) is evidenced by listings in restaurants and on the shelves of independent retailers. The orange wine phenomenon exploded between 2015 and 2022, being associated with the growth in popularity of natural wines. The new, more adventurous, drinkers loved the textural nature of the wines, which offered them the structure of red with some of the feeling of whites.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The New Spain – the name of a book, but also the move away from massively oaky wine styles towards more gastronomic wines. Spanish producers began to rediscover indigenous varieties, old vineyards, and make wines with a lighter touch. So, let’s acknowledge:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Non-fortified sherry. Sherry has always been about how wine develops over time in the cellar. But what if the wines were not fortified and farming was not just a means to produce grapes for a process? The wine world is full of experimentation, which in itself is often the rediscovery of traditional methods. Which is why we are witnessing more wines being made… &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Under &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;flor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;. We can be fairly certain that veneration of the Jura vin jaune has played a part here. But not all flor winemaking takes the process to such an extreme. Flor is a tool for the winemaker, and its presence gives a unique accent to the wine affected by it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;PET NAT! (and ancestral/col fondo wines). The market may be nearing saturation here. Many are seasonal in that you would drink them late spring into summer. Some producers are experimenting with later releases and extended lees ageing to bridge the style gap between pet nats and traditional method sparkling wines.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Austrian oak! A.K.A. you had me at Stockinger. These barrels are the ultimate wine accessory (let’s give a nod and a wink to eggs and amphorae).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded>
<wfw:commentRss>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/12/05/three-decades-in-the-wine-trade/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
</item>
<item>
<title>Small and Beautiful: A snapshot of Les Caves’s 2025 Tastings</title>
<link>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/12/02/small-and-beautiful-a-snapshot-of-les-cavess-2025-tastings/</link>
<comments>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/12/02/small-and-beautiful-a-snapshot-of-les-cavess-2025-tastings/#respond</comments>
<dc:creator>blog</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 14:54:43 +0000</pubDate>
<category>Uncategorized</category>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/?p=11604</guid>
<description>Mostly small and beautiful So many tastings, so little time. So say probably most of our customers. Not only is the calendar crammed with massive international fairs, conferences and symposiums, but back at home, there are more tasting dates (all shapes and sizes) than a dried fruit depository. Most of these are the same-old, same-old. [&amp;#8230;]</description>
<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1oTkyFxitkBE5BLn1xL4o7fIDGOqimkFN"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-11613 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1oTkyFxitkBE5BLn1xL4o7fIDGOqimkFN" alt="" width="534" height="688" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1oTkyFxitkBE5BLn1xL4o7fIDGOqimkFN 1170w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/IMG_9275-233x300.jpg 233w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/IMG_9275-796x1024.jpg 796w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/IMG_9275-768x989.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 534px) 100vw, 534px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Mostly small and beautiful&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;So many tastings, so little time. So say probably most of our customers.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Not only is the calendar crammed with massive international fairs, conferences and symposiums, but back at home, there are more tasting dates (all shapes and sizes) than a dried fruit depository.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Most of these are the same-old, same-old. Wines opened and poured, fact sheets fact-checked, ten-second blurred transactions. The large-scale ones are completely impersonal, often dwarfed by their surroundings, commercial examples of “feel the width”. One company went full throttle by annexing The Royal Opera House to show off their wines. Good for them! Then there is the hipster-friendly grungy location, in a dive or a bar, or a gallery or using a blank space. Some tastings are blink-and-you-will-miss-them, pop up in restaurants between service, a more guerrilla-type approach.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;This year, Les Caves de Pyrene held six events in London and one each in Leeds and Manchester, as well as wine dinners and grower takeovers.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Is there a useful point to generic tastings? Only customers can say. Do they attend for a specific reason (changing a list, educational purpose, the social catch-up). Does a tasting result in new listings and quantifiable sales? If the follow up is precise and immediate and the attendees in question kept notes and had a keen feeling about certain wines.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;This year, Les Caves de Pyrene held six events in London and one each in Leeds and Manchester, as well as wine dinners and grower takeovers.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Or are most tastings a form of PR mood music, to remind our customers that we exist, showing that we can put on a good event, that our selection of wines is strong, that we have identifiable specialisms. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Of course, trade customers are becoming blasé about tastings. Something always seems to come up. An attendance of 50% and above is remarkable these days. In one sense, this is understandable, when one tasting morphs into another. Disappointing when you know how much time goes into organising an event.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;The New Old Georgia&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1K6DeZ32m13rn85Y8CsVuyMVP1xFiAmZ4"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-11462 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1K6DeZ32m13rn85Y8CsVuyMVP1xFiAmZ4" alt="" width="546" height="541" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1K6DeZ32m13rn85Y8CsVuyMVP1xFiAmZ4 472w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-15-at-11.30.51-AM-300x297.png 300w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-15-at-11.30.51-AM-150x150.png 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 546px) 100vw, 546px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Organised in cahoots with &lt;a href="https://www.sagerandwine.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Sager &amp;amp; Wine&lt;/a&gt;, our 2025 tasting season kicked off at Lyle’s (RIP) and marked the arrival of all new vintages and some new wines from Georgia, the aim being to demonstrate the diversity of wines from that country, from the more traditional and deeper skin-contact wines to the fresher, less extractive styles. With examples from twenty-one producers making wine in nine separate regions of the country, this was indeed a wine tour de Georgia, featuring some of the most reputed and innovative growers.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;Savoie Faire x (Arguably) The First and Last Comparative Gringet Tasting&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Our Savoie portfolio is small but perfectly formed with delicious wines made from unique, indigenous grapes. We saw an opportunity to pop open exciting regional examples ranging from glacial Chasselas to brooding Mondeuse. The double-header tasting also featured a separate homage to the late Dominique Belluard, who famously (if you are a wine nerd!) championed the native Gringet grape, a variety found locally in Ayze in the Haute-Savoie. To this end, we gathered fifteen iterations of Gringet, two from Dominique, the rest from his friends (mostly from the 2021 vintage). Gringet proved to be a noble variety, each producer imprinting their personality onto the wine in question.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Savoie wine of the tasting – everything was bang on, but the Les Vignes du Paradis wines were exceptional&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Gringet of the tasting: Ganevat’s Le Feu (although Lapalu’s Feu Follet was beautiful, too).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;More Splosh For Your Dosh&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1R73tPEJ9wfO798-1mIn1j3IkJzkZdYPr"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-11463 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1R73tPEJ9wfO798-1mIn1j3IkJzkZdYPr" alt="" width="548" height="539" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1R73tPEJ9wfO798-1mIn1j3IkJzkZdYPr 587w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-15-at-11.33.28-AM-300x295.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 548px) 100vw, 548px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;We had been noting the dip in average wine spend from both our on-trade and retail customers and felt that it would be a good idea to prove that one could buy wines at a relatively painless price without compromising quality.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Bang-for-buck as a tasting title being &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;verboten&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;, it was a toss-up between the uber-whimsical tagline above (the other being More Splash For Your Cash). Well, we like a bit of vulgar in our lives. Although most of the reps rolled their eyes and shuddered, the idea itself could not be sniffed at.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;You don’t sell wine by the cliché. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;In the end, the tasting featured 120 wines with a particular focus – the vast majority retailing under £20, made from organically or biodynamically farmed grapes, and in most cases, vinified in a low-intervention style. Affordable gems. And better than Poundland. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;Kindred Spirits&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1fCkyezG2tFA0j7zHnvWPjc9DPlGSs-YX"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-11607 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1fCkyezG2tFA0j7zHnvWPjc9DPlGSs-YX" alt="" width="532" height="658" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1fCkyezG2tFA0j7zHnvWPjc9DPlGSs-YX 308w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Screenshot-2025-12-02-at-9.48.18-AM-243x300.png 243w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 532px) 100vw, 532px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;I can call spirits from the vasty deep&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Glendower ~ Henry IV, Part 1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The spirituous kindred folk in this case being Caroline Rozes (Domaine d’Aurensan); Laurent Cazottes (Maison Distillerie Cazottes); Barney Wilzak (Capreolus Distillery) and Jean-Luc Josse (Vinmouth) who came to Brawn in London to demonstrate the sheer quality and versatility of their spirits, how they can be an active infusive element in cocktails, and finally, during dinner, how they might perform when matched to certain dishes. We wanted sommeliers, bar managers and chefs to taste the purity and complexity of these elixirs and to think about ways to bring them into their wine, cocktail and food menus.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1RRoCWPAL0-VcjksQzsCT9yqoRxp-45bO"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-11608 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1RRoCWPAL0-VcjksQzsCT9yqoRxp-45bO" alt="" width="531" height="658" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1RRoCWPAL0-VcjksQzsCT9yqoRxp-45bO 490w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Screenshot-2025-12-02-at-9.49.56-AM-242x300.png 242w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 531px) 100vw, 531px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;(Our First Ever) Champagne x Burgundy Tasting&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Cinders, you shall go to the ball. Our Champagne selection has grown considerably over the last couple of years, and we are justifiably proud of the quality of these wines. Burgundy was the obvious dancing partner to bolster the tasting. Five producers came to London (the tasting and wine dinner were held in Wild By Tart in Belgravia) to pour and talk about their wines. We opened some special wines too, which points to one of the major benefits of a focused trade tasting, that a single sample may be tasted by up to 40 customers.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1LPb7KZTfagDzf1ZzabMSwzhaX0ubAWbc"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-11609 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1LPb7KZTfagDzf1ZzabMSwzhaX0ubAWbc" alt="" width="532" height="529" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1LPb7KZTfagDzf1ZzabMSwzhaX0ubAWbc 689w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Screenshot-2025-12-02-at-9.52.12-AM-300x298.png 300w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Screenshot-2025-12-02-at-9.52.12-AM-150x150.png 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 532px) 100vw, 532px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Wines of Settentrione &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The counterpart of our Southern Italian and the Islands tasting a couple of years ago called Mezzogiorno, this was our deep dive into the wines of the northern and central regions. Ok, I am taking a liberty with Lazio! Six producers attended and a line-up stacked with quality. From Barbera to Barolo, from Slarina to Sangiovese, from Valpolicellas of Veneto to the Vitovskas from Carso this was a Giro of the north, a wine tour de force.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Stay in the loop and never miss a tasting! Contact us to request to be added to our mailing list:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;shop@lescaves.co.uk&lt;/strong&gt; |  &lt;strong&gt;sales@lescaves.co.uk&lt;/strong&gt; | 01483 538820&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
<wfw:commentRss>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/12/02/small-and-beautiful-a-snapshot-of-les-cavess-2025-tastings/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
</item>
<item>
<title>What Makes a Wine Popular?</title>
<link>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/11/26/what-makes-a-wine-popular/</link>
<comments>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/11/26/what-makes-a-wine-popular/#respond</comments>
<dc:creator>blog</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 13:18:04 +0000</pubDate>
<category>Uncategorized</category>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/?p=11601</guid>
<description>&amp;#160; Reputation can refer to renown (widespread fame) or esteem (the regard in which something is held). It is something that feeds on itself and grows larger until such time as the next big thing comes along. A wine becomes popular when it is generally deemed to have a good reputation although the means by [&amp;#8230;]</description>
<content:encoded>&lt;figure id="attachment_10509" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-10509" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=120YA4Pw4JRiF1sMFKbBxEnzJfxCuCntt"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-10509" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=120YA4Pw4JRiF1sMFKbBxEnzJfxCuCntt" alt="" width="650" height="493" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=120YA4Pw4JRiF1sMFKbBxEnzJfxCuCntt 650w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/Pierre-Dietrich-RWF22-300x228.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption id="caption-attachment-10509" class="wp-caption-text"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Real Wine Fair 2022&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Reputation can refer to renown (widespread fame) or esteem (the regard in which something is held). It is something that feeds on itself and grows larger until such time as the next big &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;thing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; comes along. A wine becomes popular when it is generally deemed to have a good reputation although the means by which this is acquired may differ.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Perceived rarity and desirability contribute enormously to the popularity of certain wines, the aura of mystery being a lucrative asset in this regard. Such wines may end up as commodities traded on the grey market or commanding exalted prices at auction. However good they are (and many such wines may be vastly overrated), they become prestige products bought to augment the cellars of wealthy private clients or flipped for a quick profit. When customers see these wines on restaurant wine lists, they may naturally presume that the lofty price is merited and even if they cannot afford to buy the particular wine, will still aspire to buy it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Some certainties have disappeared. The rankings or scores (sometimes known as Parkerisation) associated with giving wines their high reputation are less important now. Individuals are just as likely to listen to the recommendation of a friend or look online for information on a wine as to be influenced by a mark out of one hundred. Perhaps, also, the wines designed to impress critics and accrue high scores as a result, are not so much in fashion.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;In these straitened times when so many wines are priced out of the pockets of consumers, perceived value-for-money will help to make a wine more popular. When a particular wine is qualitatively better than others at a similar price point and obviously overdelivers, it gains a loyal audience who are often searching for a “house wine” that they can buy again and again knowing they are getting an excellent deal. The wine may be commercial in style or utterly distinctive, an appellation or a table wine, it is that when a customer drinks it, they appreciate its undoubted value.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Value-for-money may be one benchmark of wine popularity. Conversely,  wines that are highly reputed and reassuringly expensive are often considered must-haves, if a wine list is deemed to tick all the boxes. Such wines garner their reputations over time and are collectively rated by critics, journalists, influencers, restaurateurs and sommeliers until such a time as they become iconic in their own right.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Charismatic or larger-than-life producers with interesting stories to tell or persuasive philosophies to expound are the ambassadors for their own brand and also help to raise awareness of the region in which they are making wine.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Wines become popular often for the simple reason that their time has come. Trends happen because people want them to happen. Each country has had its day in the sun.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The label – alas -matters. Responses to label designs are, of course, highly subjective, yet they can help to sell the wine. In some cases, the label may transcend the humble contents within the bottle. Conversely, an unassuming or dreary label can affect the sales of a superb wine.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Advertising is overrated as a means of popularising wines, but social media plays a significant role as does simple word of mouth. The actions of wine merchants have more power than one thinks. Many years ago I made a conscious effort to sell more Muscadet by putting samples in every customer tasting and suggesting that this appellation was the new Chablis and the next big thing. This was a self-fulfilling prophecy – we tripled our sales of Muscadet in that year alone, and a few months later I was invited to attend a round table wine magazine discussion to assess why Muscadet had suddenly taken off so remarkably in the trade. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;I don’t take credit for the irresistible rise of Muscadet. Wines become popular often for the simple reason that their time has come. Trends happen because people want them to happen. Talking about the next big thing is not enough in itself. Getting hard listings so that consumers see the wines wherever they go, persuading the trade to talk about their new best-selling wines – these are the concrete measures required to make a wine really popular.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Tastes change with the generations. For a start, more people drink wine than ever and across the socio-economic classes. When I was first introduced to wine,  choice was limited, and hierarchies were apparent. You had the classics (cru classé Bordeaux, Burgundy from famous estate, the wines of Piedmont and Tuscany, Californians, German Riesling and so on) and you had supermarket wine. After this came the vogue for all things New World and varietal, from plump Aussie Chardonnay and Shiraz, New Zealand Sauvignon and later on Chilean Cabernet Sauvignon and Argentinean Malbec. Each country has had its day in the sun. Reputation is dependent on PR and getting wines in front of influencers (be they bloggers, journalists or wine educators).  A lot of money is spent by wine organisations to secure influence. Yet with all this PR clamour, no single voice stands out. When every grape variety seems to have its own day in the calendar, when articles on every region in the wine world are being published regularly (proclaiming that they are the next big thing), the nature of popularity itself becomes more transient.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Popularity might be measured in brute sales and sheer growth, but these are dependent on how major markets across the world are performing at a given time, which in turn are dependent on tariffs, taxes and other trade barriers.  If for some reason, high tariffs say, a market effectively shuts down, it does not mean that the wines have become less popular, rather that they have become artificially less affordable.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Consumers should taste a wine on its merits and without reference to its reputation. Just because a wine may be popular does not mean that it is good. Or even that you have to like it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
<wfw:commentRss>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/11/26/what-makes-a-wine-popular/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
</item>
<item>
<title>Polyphonic Singing, Wine and Georgian Culture</title>
<link>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/11/24/georgian-polyphonic-singing/</link>
<comments>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/11/24/georgian-polyphonic-singing/#respond</comments>
<dc:creator>blog</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 16:02:22 +0000</pubDate>
<category>Uncategorized</category>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/?p=11590</guid>
<description>Popular singing has a highly valued place in Georgian culture. Polyphonic singing, in the Georgian language, is a secular tradition in a country whose language and culture have often been oppressed by invaders. There are three types of polyphony in Georgia: complex polyphony, which is common in Svaneti; polyphonic dialogue over a bass background, prevalent [&amp;#8230;]</description>
<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1ZM1EGTp4uL3knppmMrX9YSOraoQSh_lb"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-11594 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1ZM1EGTp4uL3knppmMrX9YSOraoQSh_lb" alt="" width="766" height="499" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1ZM1EGTp4uL3knppmMrX9YSOraoQSh_lb 720w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/7H0A9481-300x195.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 766px) 100vw, 766px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Popular singing has a highly valued place in Georgian culture. Polyphonic singing, in the Georgian language, is a secular tradition in a country whose language and culture have often been oppressed by invaders. There are three types of polyphony in Georgia: complex polyphony, which is common in Svaneti; polyphonic dialogue over a bass background, prevalent in the Kakheti region in Eastern Georgia; and contrasted polyphony with three partially improvised sung parts, characteristic of western Georgia. The Chakrulo song, which is sung at ceremonies and festivals and belongs to the first category, is distinguished by its use of metaphor and its yodel, the krimanchuli and a “cockerel&amp;#8217;s crow”, performed by a male falsetto singer. Some of these songs are linked to the cult of the grapevine and many date back to the eighth century.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Many wines are blends of disparate grape varieties which come together as one in the final wine. Nowhere is more evident than in the Pheasant’s Tears Poliphonia&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;To the untrained ear, polyphonic folk singing may sound strangely discordant. But then so might the monophonic unaccompanied Gregorian chant whose repetitions often induce a meditative, even trance-like state. In polyphony, because it is technically different, one might initially search in vain for modern melodies and mellifluousness, but soon the overall sound becomes the seamless amalgam of the different voices, and one begins to anticipate the intervals and slide into the internal rhythm of the song.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure id="attachment_5838" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-5838" style="width: 323px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1W9rF9LdnI9iE6OmkxYODJYhlJf3FuLsf"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-5838" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1W9rF9LdnI9iE6OmkxYODJYhlJf3FuLsf" alt="" width="323" height="520" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1W9rF9LdnI9iE6OmkxYODJYhlJf3FuLsf 592w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/Screen-Shot-2018-10-31-at-10.02.19-AM-186x300.png 186w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 323px) 100vw, 323px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption id="caption-attachment-5838" class="wp-caption-text"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pheasant&amp;#8217;s Tears Poliphonia&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Many wines are blends of disparate grape varieties (or vineyards, or terroirs) which come together as one in the final wine. Nowhere is more evident than in the Pheasant’s Tears Poliphonia which contains perhaps 117 different Georgian varieties with a further 40 yet to be identified. When harvested, the grapes are a melange of different colours; their skins may be green, yellow, gold, orange, purple, rose-hued. All are straight pressed regardless and go into the final mix. The visual result is an appealingly orange/pinkish hazy wine with a delicious unique flavour identity. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Poliphonia is one (extreme) example of the so-called field blend, often red and white grape varieties planted together, harvested together and fermented together. A kind of wine harmony emerges, something greater than the sum of the discrete parts, at the same time nuanced in that it honours those different elements. Just like when the different voices come together (in one’s perception) to create the polyphonic song.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Thus Poliphonia can be seen as unity forged out of apparent chaos with the difference between all these many and varied grapes washing into the wholesome whole. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Its name is emblematic of a greater truth. Living in a city like London, one may witness the rich variety that people from different cultures give to the city, bringing their stories, their language, their art, their music and their culinary traditions with them from other countries. Each individual adds something different to the colour palette. In the end, we are a mixture of our genetic origins and our specific traditions but have the opportunity to absorb those of others and renew our worldview in the process. Those who complain about cultural dilution ignore thousands of years of our history of inclusiveness, wherein individuals from all over the world have come to work and live and contribute to the energy of this great city.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Poliphonia, the wine, is a valuable archive of many forgotten grape varieties. As a wine with colour (and yet without a definable colour), with flavours (yet without a single obvious one to pin down), it conveys the shifting tonal notes and subtle energetic inflections of a multi (multi) blend. Such a wine reminds us that life can be more complex than black or white (or, in wine terms, red and white or even red, white and/or orange!), and that the real truth of the matter is what we receive as part of our experience and how we perceive it. Suddenly, the different seemingly discordant voices come together, and the song is heard.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Sitting down at Georgian supra the other day, at a table laden with lovingly crafted dishes vibrating with colour and diverse ingredients, the orange (for want of a better descriptive colour) wine glinting in the glass, I felt that this wine, diversity incarnate, at this moment, was specifically designed for the food and the different guests each with their unique experiences. As if the wine symbolised the social bonding that occurs when friends – and indeed strangers – sit down together around a table, the time when individuals become as one family.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-2932 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1JbaC_unfRG4hmjEjwCFZmhYsz6QzbZJH" alt="" width="563" height="375" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1JbaC_unfRG4hmjEjwCFZmhYsz6QzbZJH 680w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Georgia-300x199.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 563px) 100vw, 563px" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;At Les Caves de Pyrene, we were one of the first companies to explore Georgia’s rich wine culture. We began to ship a handful of wines from this country in 2011, and now work with no fewer than 17 producers and nearly fifty wines. Over the years, we have hosted numerous supras (banquets) and held trade tastings focused exclusively on these wines. We hold Georgia and her artisan winemakers in deep regard. Read more about Georgian wine &lt;a href="https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2023/05/24/a-brief-overview-of-georgian-wine-culture/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;here,&lt;/a&gt; and about the famed Georgian supra &lt;a href="https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/08/11/wine-and-the-supra/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Interested in finding out more about the nearly 50 Georgian wines we bring in? Contact us directly:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;shop@lescaves.co.uk&lt;/strong&gt; |  &lt;strong&gt;sales@lescaves.co.uk&lt;/strong&gt; | 01483 538820&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
<wfw:commentRss>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/11/24/georgian-polyphonic-singing/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
</item>
<item>
<title>Fizzical Education</title>
<link>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/11/21/fizzical-education/</link>
<comments>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/11/21/fizzical-education/#respond</comments>
<dc:creator>blog</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 14:54:18 +0000</pubDate>
<category>Uncategorized</category>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/?p=11574</guid>
<description>Les Caves doesn’t do Champagne and Burgundy tastings until they do. And so it came to pass with our inaugural punt into these regions on Monday October 13th at London&amp;#8217;s Wild By Tart. This tasting arose out of our desire to exhibit our increasing portfolio of small champagne producers, that region where we have hitherto [&amp;#8230;]</description>
<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=108qwHFpr_skaCBbome1c4yyZFA1B9dvW"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-11587 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=108qwHFpr_skaCBbome1c4yyZFA1B9dvW" alt="" width="479" height="637" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=108qwHFpr_skaCBbome1c4yyZFA1B9dvW 623w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Wild-by-Tart-tasting-226x300.jpg 226w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 479px) 100vw, 479px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Les Caves doesn’t do Champagne and Burgundy tastings until they do. And so it came to pass with our inaugural punt into these regions on Monday October 13&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;th&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; at London&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="https://www.wildbytart.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Wild By Tart&lt;/a&gt;. This tasting arose out of our desire to exhibit our increasing portfolio of small champagne producers, that region where we have hitherto been a very poor relation. Now we are very confident about the quality of these artisan vignerons from Champagne and wanted to show also the sheer variety of styles, connected by the fact these guys are not just making bubbles qua bubbles, they are making gastronomic wines.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;A little word about dosage. Only one of the wines listed below has a dosage of above 4g/l, in other words, all the others are either extra brut or brut nature. To be able to achieve this, you require excellent ripe grapes, otherwise the champagne will taste acidic. Although conventional champagne is largely based on blending to a house style, it is instructive to taste wines that are vinified by parcel or where the grape variety takes centre stage (Taillet for Meunier; Vauversin for Chardonnay; Marie-Courtin for Pinot Noir) and we can sense clearly the origin of the grapes.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;Maxime Blin, Trigny&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The 12-hectares of vines are exclusively planted in the village of Trigny, making the champagnes from the estate ‘mono-crus’ or single-village wines, very rare in the Champagne region. They became ‘vignerons independents’ in 1988 under the impetus of Gilles, Maxime&amp;#8217;s father. Maxime returned to the estate in 2005, followed by his wife Claire in 2013. They opted to go down the organic route in 2018, and the vineyard has been certified organic since 2021 with first organic wine arriving in 2022. Dosage is low – around extra brut level, and the entry level Carte Blanche is bottled Brut Nature.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1dfNvwWGRkdrvf1CjX3zaod-KBn7W9i-n"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-11576 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1dfNvwWGRkdrvf1CjX3zaod-KBn7W9i-n" alt="" width="302" height="754" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1dfNvwWGRkdrvf1CjX3zaod-KBn7W9i-n 420w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Maxime-Blin-Champagne-Carte-Blanche-NL-120x300.jpg 120w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Maxime-Blin-Champagne-Carte-Blanche-NL-410x1024.jpg 410w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 302px) 100vw, 302px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;NV Carte Blanche Brut Nature ~ 80% Pinot Meunier, 20% Pinot Noir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;NV Grande Tradition Extra Brut ~ 90% Chardonnay, 10% Pinot Noir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;2012 Ailes de Psyché Extra Brut ~ 100% Pinot Noir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jean-Paul Deville, Verzenay&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Founded in 1969, Jean-Paul Deville is a family owned and run estate in Champagne. They own most of their vineyards (around 20 hectares) but buy in a small amount of grapes from growers under contract. Their vineyards are situated throughout the Champagne region with some in the Cotes des Blancs (Chardonnay vines on limestone and chalk) whilst the Pinot Noir vines are on clay-limestone. The wines are now made by Marie-Alice Deville, and the vineyards are farmed organically (with certification).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1tUa0KdnsQxO359gFAw2otsgN2eui5i3e"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-11577 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1tUa0KdnsQxO359gFAw2otsgN2eui5i3e" alt="" width="303" height="756" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1tUa0KdnsQxO359gFAw2otsgN2eui5i3e 420w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Deville-Champagne-Carte-Noire-120x300.jpg 120w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Deville-Champagne-Carte-Noire-410x1024.jpg 410w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 303px) 100vw, 303px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;NV Carte Noire Brut  ~ 75% Pinot Noir, 20% Chardonnay, 5% Pinot Meunier&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hugues Godmé, Verzenay &amp;amp; Verzy&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Hugues is the fifth generation to grow champagne in Verzenay. He has provided 40 years of technical knowledge necessary for the management of the vineyards and the development of their wines. He owns 11 hectares, 40 plots of vines spread over four villages of the Montagne de Reims: Verzenay, Verzy, Villers-Marmery and Villedommange . Since 2006, they began farming organically (certified in 2013) then biodynamically (certified in 2014). For Godmé, top-quality vineyard work is of utmost importance for later quality in the glass. &amp;#8220;When I see the grapes hanging on the vine, I already know how the champagne will taste later.&amp;#8221; This philosophy allows Godmé to produce Champagnes expressing the subtlety and strength of the terroirs of which they are from. The non-vintage wines have around 50% reserve wine to bolster them. The vintage wines (Les Champs St Martin &amp;amp; Les Alouettes Saint Bets 1er cru) are aged for 96 months sur lattes &amp;#8211; and are sensationally profound.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=16rOk2NHxGwMI5jSP9oMpjxeisD6MFE8d"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-11578 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=16rOk2NHxGwMI5jSP9oMpjxeisD6MFE8d" alt="" width="302" height="754" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=16rOk2NHxGwMI5jSP9oMpjxeisD6MFE8d 420w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Godme-Blanc-de-Noirs-120x300.jpg 120w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Godme-Blanc-de-Noirs-410x1024.jpg 410w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 302px) 100vw, 302px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;NV Les Terres Unions Brut Nature ~ 1/3 each Pinot Noir, Chardonnay, Meunier&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;NV Blanc de Noirs Grand Cru Brut Nature ~ 100% Pinot Noir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;2013 Les Champs Martin Grand Cru Brut Nature ~ 100% Pinot Noir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;2012 Les Alouettes St Bets 1er Cru Brut Nature ~ 100% Chardonnay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;2018 Rose de Maceration Brut Nature ~ 100% Pinot Noir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;Maurice Delabaye, Damery&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;For five generations, the Delabaye family has cultivated vines with dedication and deep respect for the Champagne tradition. Their 10-hectare estate is located in the heart of the Marne Valley, near Épernay, and extends across 10 villages, including parcels classified as Grand Cru and Premier Cru. The estate grows the three classic Champagne grape varieties (Pinot Meunier, Pinot Noir, and Chardonnay) each selected for its unique role in expressing the region’s character. All grapes are pressed on-site, allowing full control over the vinification process. With meticulous blending and time-honoured methods, Delabaye crafts wines that capture the essence of their terroir. Each cuvée is aged in deep cellars at a constant 10°C, where time and silence shape the house’s elegant and distinctive style. All the wines are extra brut or zero dosage.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1bedMYsQWINoI57EYldHKZwUV0Eb9m0Vb"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-11579 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1bedMYsQWINoI57EYldHKZwUV0Eb9m0Vb" alt="" width="302" height="427" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1bedMYsQWINoI57EYldHKZwUV0Eb9m0Vb 1241w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Maurice-Delabaye-promesse-label-212x300.jpg 212w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Maurice-Delabaye-promesse-label-724x1024.jpg 724w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Maurice-Delabaye-promesse-label-768x1086.jpg 768w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Maurice-Delabaye-promesse-label-1086x1536.jpg 1086w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 302px) 100vw, 302px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;NV Promesse Extra Brut ~ Pinot Noir, Pinot Meunier, Chardonnay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;NV Prestige 1er cru Brut Nature ~ Pinot Noir, Pinot Meunier, Chardonnay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;NV Blanc de Blanc 1er cru Brut Nature ~ 100% Chardonnay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;NV Grand Cru Brut Nature ~ 90% Pinot Noir, 10% Chardonnay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;NV Rosé Premier Cru Brut Nature ~ 90% Chardonnay, 5% Pinot Noir, 5% Pinot Meunier&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;Eric Taillet, Baslieux-sous-Châtillon&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Based in Baslieux-sous-Châtillon in the Belval Valley, the domaine is composed of 6 hectares of Meunier for the most part (82%), a little bit of Chardonnay and Pinot Noir and some forgotten varieties like Pinot Gris, Petit Meslier and Arbane. Eric jokes he was baptised in Champagne and that he became a winemaker as a result. Founded in 1956, Champagne Taillet marketed its first bottled in 1961. Eric (fourth generation) took over the domaine in 1995 with modern and sustainable ideas while using a lot of manual work. His winemaking philosophy is a little different from what is usually done in the area. He is inspired by a certain phrase &amp;#8220;Meunier, tu dors” (&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;meunier&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;, you sleep) meaning you must leave it alone. The less one intervenes, the better it will express itself. Most of their cuvees are made from Meunier only. Today, Eric works alongside his children Dylan and Léna Taillet. Progressive organic and biodynamic work in the vines assists healthy grape production and low intervention winemaking carries on the good work. Dosage is low, ranging from 1 g/.l to 2.5 g/l.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1xcYRsQM4Y35RC2XgU8AYAa7VtuBa5DC5"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-11580 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1xcYRsQM4Y35RC2XgU8AYAa7VtuBa5DC5" alt="" width="302" height="754" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1xcYRsQM4Y35RC2XgU8AYAa7VtuBa5DC5 420w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Taillet-Champagne-ExlusivT-Extra-Brut-120x300.jpg 120w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Taillet-Champagne-ExlusivT-Extra-Brut-410x1024.jpg 410w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 302px) 100vw, 302px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;NV Egali’T Brut ~ 95% Meunier, 2.5% each Chardonnay &amp;amp; Pinot Noir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;NV Exclusivi’T Extra Brut ~ 100% Meunier&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;2019 Bansionensi Extra Brut ~ 100% Meunier&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;Laurent Vauversin, Oger, Côtes des Blancs&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Maison Vauversin, currently managed by Laurent Vauversin and his father Bruno, has existed since the 17th century. In 1640, Nicolas de Vauversin was the first to plant vines in the little village of Oger (near the town of Épernay), on the Côtes des Blancs. Fifteen generations succeeded him. In 1930, Bruno’s grandfather Fernand Vauversin, became a pioneer: he stopped selling his grapes to local merchants and decided to commercialize his own champagne.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Laurent loves his vineyard above all, not as a production site but as a complete ecosystem he needs to protect, with its rhythm, its biodiversity, its soul… The entire estate was consequently switched to organic winemaking in 2011. He wants to create the best possible and most sensible transition, between preserving centuries of experience and new, contemporary impulses and visions.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The winery received certification in 2014, making it the first organic house in Oger. Biodiversity in the vineyard has been particularly important to Vauversin. The vineyard plots are enriched with diversified seedlings (cereals, legumes, flowers, etc.), more perennial plantations of aromatics (lavender, rosemary, sage, etc.) and various different types of tree. Laurent believes that when a positive energy is cultivated in the soil and the vines, it is carried over to the people who enjoy his champagnes.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;All champagnes are vinified with native yeasts at ambient temperatures and are not filtered. They contain very little sulphur (less than 35mg/l). The riddling takes place by hand in the natural cellar. All the wines are extra brut; some are zero dosage. Beautiful expressions of the chalky soils of the Côtes des Blancs, capable of long-ageing whilst being delicate and even ethereal.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1Tld4d-Mo4Wbl48P4tn5H7h4RvIJY5NzO"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-11581 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1Tld4d-Mo4Wbl48P4tn5H7h4RvIJY5NzO" alt="" width="302" height="754" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1Tld4d-Mo4Wbl48P4tn5H7h4RvIJY5NzO 420w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Vauversin-Champagne-Les-Crayeres-120x300.jpg 120w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Vauversin-Champagne-Les-Crayeres-410x1024.jpg 410w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 302px) 100vw, 302px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;NV Original Blanc de Blancs Grand Cru Extra Brut – 100% Chardonnay &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;NV Orpair Blanc de Blancs Grand Cru Extra Brut &amp;#8211; 100% Chardonnay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;2020 Les Crayères Blanc de Blancs Grand Cru Brut Nature ~ 100% Chardonnay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;2019 Rossignol Blanc de Blancs Grand Cru Brut Nature  ~ 100% Chardonnay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;Thomas De Marne, Domaine des Cotannes, Ville-sur-Arce, Côte des Bar&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Champagne Thomas de Marne, a small family-run organic estate and successor to Champagne Val Frison, is nestled in the south of Champagne Ardenne, in the renowned Côte des Bar region. Valérie Frison took over her family’s vines in the village of Ville-sur-Arce in 1997, initially selling the grapes to the local cooperative. Together with her then husband, Thierry de Marne, she began converting her vineyards to organic viticulture in 2003, and in 2007, the first vintage eligible for organic certification, they began to make small quantities of their own champagne. In 2018, her son Thomas de Marne and his partner Florie Pilares returned to begin the process of taking over the estate. By the 2020 harvest, they had taken full control. Their goal is to produce wines with as close to zero additions (sulphur, sugar, enzymes, etc.) as possible. Here, their passion for organic viticulture is reflected in every bottle of champagne they produce. The wines made from grapes grown on Kimmeridgean clay are rich and intense (Pinot Noir is their speciality) and all are bottled brut nature (i.e. without dosage). These are mainly single vintage wines; all aged in Burgundian oak barrels with a limited period &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;sur lattes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1k5b1a06ov5vfpC_ExKfhLyyjzACoLRz5"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-11582 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1k5b1a06ov5vfpC_ExKfhLyyjzACoLRz5" alt="" width="302" height="754" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1k5b1a06ov5vfpC_ExKfhLyyjzACoLRz5 420w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/De-Marne-Champagne-Goustan-120x300.jpg 120w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/De-Marne-Champagne-Goustan-410x1024.jpg 410w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 302px) 100vw, 302px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;NV Goustan Brut Nature ~ 100% Pinot Noir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;NV Lalore Brut Nature ~ 100% Chardonnay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;NV Holistique Brut Nature ~ 70% Pinot Noir, 30% Chardonnay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;Maurice Choppin, Damery&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Located in Damery, just a few kilometres from Épernay, Maison Maurice Choppin has been working the unique terroirs of the Marne Valley for more than 7 generations. Proud of his family heritage and his humble approach to living things, Benjamin Choppin makes natural and distinctive wines that are powerful, well rounded and balanced. Inspired by the &amp;#8220;Belle Champagne&amp;#8221;, he values its exceptional heritage and shines the light on the work of the winemaker. Chardonnay thrives here on the calcareous soils, and the wines are all bottled extra brut (around 3 g/l).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;NV Les Arpents Extra Brut ~ 85% Pinot Meunier, 10% Chardonnay, 5% Pinot Noir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;NV Les Mi-Cotes Extra Brut ~ 60% Chardonnay, 40% Pinot Meunier&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;2018 Damery Extra Brut  ~80% Chardonnay, 20% Pinot Meunier&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;2017 Epinette de Champagne Extra Brut ~ 100% Chardonnay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;Marie-Courtin, Polisot, Côte des Bar&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Dominique Moreau was born and bought up in the champagne region. She explains that there, everyone had a piece of land and also vines- it was the norm. Her great-grandmother, Marie Courtin, farmed her land herself, using a horse during the First World War while the menfolk were away on the front. Dominique’s estate is located on land that has always been owned by her family, but they had rented it out to tenant farmers. From the age of eighteen years-old she was working on the land amongst vines. She worked part-time as a teacher in a professional viticulture school and spent the hours when she was not teaching, farming vines. She took over the family estate in 2000 when the previous tenant farmers retired. She began converting her vines to organic farming in 2005. Pinot Noir flourishes on the Kimmeridgean marls, although she has some Chardonnay and Pinot Blanc also. Most of the wines are brut nature and v little added sulphites – Concordance is zero added. The wines are named after emotions and energies.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1aj_FBeS7UuaQmftAwlACHQS_c1rJdy5r"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-11584 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1aj_FBeS7UuaQmftAwlACHQS_c1rJdy5r" alt="" width="302" height="754" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1aj_FBeS7UuaQmftAwlACHQS_c1rJdy5r 559w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Marie-Courtin-Champagne-Concordance--120x300.jpg 120w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Marie-Courtin-Champagne-Concordance--410x1024.jpg 410w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 302px) 100vw, 302px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;202o Blanc de Blancs Presence Extra Brut ~ 60% Chardonnay, 40% Pinot Blanc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;2020 Blanc de Noirs Amphora Extra Brut ~ 100% Pinot Noir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;2020 Blanc de Blanc Eloquence Extra Brut ~ 100% Chardonnay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;2017 Efflorescence Extra Brut ~ 100% Pinot Noir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;2017 Concordance Extra Brut ~ 100% Pinot Noir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Interested in finding out more about the wines mentioned? Contact us directly:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;shop@lescaves.co.uk&lt;/strong&gt; |  &lt;strong&gt;sales@lescaves.co.uk&lt;/strong&gt; | 01483 538820&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
<wfw:commentRss>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/11/21/fizzical-education/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
</item>
<item>
<title>Coming Soon a Wine List Near You</title>
<link>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/11/18/coming-soon-a-wine-list-near-you/</link>
<comments>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/11/18/coming-soon-a-wine-list-near-you/#respond</comments>
<dc:creator>blog</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 13:25:35 +0000</pubDate>
<category>Uncategorized</category>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/?p=11561</guid>
<description>&amp;#160; They’re here! (Poltergeist) To whet your thirst, the following newbies are on order now, nestled in LCB and awaiting your surprise and delight: Beulah Violetta, Umbria Beulah, peel me a grape (Mae West, I’m No Angel) Beulah Violetta may sound like a character from Gone With The Wind, but in (wine) reality is a [&amp;#8230;]</description>
<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1IowVXydv6mbsKFboEleW6fBlBKvFx4mI"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-11564 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1IowVXydv6mbsKFboEleW6fBlBKvFx4mI" alt="" width="406" height="633" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1IowVXydv6mbsKFboEleW6fBlBKvFx4mI 406w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/IMG_9030-192x300.jpg 192w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 406px) 100vw, 406px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;They’re here! (Poltergeist)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;To whet your thirst, the following newbies are on order now, nestled&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; in LCB and awaiting your surprise and delight:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;b&gt;Beulah Violetta, Umbria&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Beulah, peel me a grape (Mae West, I’m No Angel)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.beulahviolettavineyard.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Beulah Violetta&lt;/a&gt; may sound like a character from Gone With The Wind, but in (wine) reality is a biodynamic farm and vineyard established in early 2022 by Annie Conley, chef and food/travel writer, and James Hird, an award-winning sommelier and one of the co-founders of Rootstock, the legendary natural wine in Sydney. After years of searching across Europe (including Beaujolais, Tuscany, and Piedmont) they found their ideal site near the hilltop town of Todi in Umbria, drawn by its elevation, soils, and wild, untouched surroundings. Named after their grandmothers (Beulah and Violet), the property now has 10.5 hectares under vine, planted with Sangiovese, Ciliegiolo, Trebbiano, Trebbiano Spoletino, and Merlot, with Sagrantino replanted to Ciliegiolo in 2025.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1imrCVGiukjEdVuy-wr3El7BoAmEjmwgj"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-11566 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1imrCVGiukjEdVuy-wr3El7BoAmEjmwgj" alt="" width="464" height="696" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1imrCVGiukjEdVuy-wr3El7BoAmEjmwgj 450w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/James-and-Annie_Beulah-violetta-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 464px) 100vw, 464px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The vineyards, facing east and north east, sit at 450 to 550 metres above sea level, mainly on clay soils with some limestone. The elevation, natural cooling, and steady winds help keep the vines healthy and reduce the risk of disease.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The older vines are dry-farmed, and while irrigation exists for new plantings, it has never been used thanks to the site’s moisture-retentive soils and use of cover crops. Yields typically range from 3 to 5 tonnes of fruit per hectare. Around 4.3 hectares were in production in 2023, increasing annually with no further plantings planned. The farm also produces wheat for pasta, olives for oil, and is home to 15 chickens and 15 beehives. Since its purchase, the entire property has been in conversion to biodynamic viticulture, with a commitment to low-intervention, regenerative farming that reflects the unique microclimate and character of the site.&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1fULjLEbi3_luzrsQ5RTX_8X2HN9Rt0eY"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-11567 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1fULjLEbi3_luzrsQ5RTX_8X2HN9Rt0eY" alt="" width="643" height="454" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1fULjLEbi3_luzrsQ5RTX_8X2HN9Rt0eY 1202w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/StessoStesso_Front1-300x212.png 300w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/StessoStesso_Front1-1024x723.png 1024w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/StessoStesso_Front1-768x542.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 643px) 100vw, 643px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The blend of the Stesso Stesso is 60% Sangiovese, 30% Merlot, 10% Sagrantino. Grapes are harvested by hand and whole bunches undergo a three-day carbonic maceration, are pressed into stainless tanks, co-fermented, and further matured for 6 months before bottling without filtration, fining and less than 20 ppm of sulphites added.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Stesso Stesso, meaning &amp;#8220;same same,&amp;#8221; reflects the consistent philosophy behind the wine’s production: minimal intervention, handpicked fruit, and a focus on expressing the unique vineyard site. It’s a playful nod to doing things the same way across vintages while still learning and evolving with the land.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Light and ethereal red with freshness at the fore with some Italian rustic sanguineness too with wild bramble fruit, wild herbs, baking spice lurking in the depths. Think Italian Beaujolais still in touch with its wilder side. A heartfelt red from the heart of Italy.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;2023 Stesso Stesso&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ansitz Dornach, Alto-Adige&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Re-habbing A-A, or &lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;new beauties in Süd-Tirol&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Once upon a time, o best beloved, we cornered the market in Alto-Adige. If there was a legend, we snaffled it. Our list was littered with great names: Georg Ramoser, Tenuta Falkenstein, Peter Pliger, Bruno Gottardi, Castel Juval, Köfererhof, Cantina Valle Isarco, amongst others. Look on my Works, ye Mighty, and despair.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;And then there were none. How the Dolo-mighty had fallen.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Now, having screwed our courage to the sticking point, we are back with &lt;a href="https://www.ansitzdornach.it/en/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Ansitz Dornach&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;In&lt;/span&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;1836 Anton von Gelmini zu Kreuzhof purchased Dornach. It was his son Max, afterwards who moulded the estate into its current shape with single terraced vineyards parted by dry walls.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1RVdxIAZrk7u88Go8BU7mxG4j_IdrSS9Q"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-11569 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1RVdxIAZrk7u88Go8BU7mxG4j_IdrSS9Q" alt="" width="655" height="316" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1RVdxIAZrk7u88Go8BU7mxG4j_IdrSS9Q 2439w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Louis-Rosso-2024-300x145.jpg 300w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Louis-Rosso-2024-1024x493.jpg 1024w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Louis-Rosso-2024-768x370.jpg 768w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Louis-Rosso-2024-1536x740.jpg 1536w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Louis-Rosso-2024-2048x987.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 655px) 100vw, 655px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Over 170 years later, Patrich Uccelli took over the small plots of land in Dornach from his mother, began overseeing the vineyards, leaning into biodynamics and becoming one of the first members of Alois Lageder&amp;#8217;s co-operative. He has been bottling his own wines following his notion of “sustainable” wines for around ten years, creating a farm that is as self-sufficient as possible. The location above the village of Salorno, a particularly cool and windy area at the bottom of Alto Adige, favours slow and balanced maturation for the grapes. Meanwhile, everything in the winery is done with as little intervention as possible in order to keep the wines as lifted and drinkable as possible.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The true embodiment of living in harmony with nature can be found at Dornach. The ideals of biodynamics are beautifully rendered here where grapes, other fruits, vegetables, grains, bees and livestock all exist harmoniously creating a closed ecosystem with amazing biodiversity. Patrick is accompanied in this endeavour by his wife, Karoline, and their two children.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The wines burst with varietal and regional character, pure expressions of site and personality.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Louis Pinot Grigio is a macerated white wine from a very mineral area at 400 meters above sea level, rich in porphyry, an extrusive volcanic rock (also known as rhyolite). Harvest is manual with spontaneous fermentation in steel from indigenous yeasts and whole bunch maceration for a few days. Ageing takes place in cement and lasts a few months before bottling. The nose recalls summer fruits, yellow peach and apricot, flowers and acacia honey, and after a few minutes vegetal notes tending towards balsamic and oriental spices emerge. In the mouth the wine is full and enveloping, with light yet velvety tannins.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Pinot Blanc/Bianco needs complex soils, perfect sun exposure and a good breeze. Dornach, sitting at an elevation of 350 metres, is perfectly positioned to grow world class Pinot Blanc, and the farm’s embrace of the natural world and deft touch in the cellar creates a wine with intense, crystalline personality and passion. This cuvee blends Chardonnay (40%) for lovely added texture and complexity.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The Traminer Aromatico is fermented and aged in large acacia barrels. Its multifaceted nose leans decisively toward oriental spices, cloves, and even nutmeg, followed by tropical fruit and hints of acacia, interspersed with flowers and honey. On the palate, it is light and drinkable, dry, and dynamic.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;A stunner, Dornach&amp;#8217;s alpine Pinot Noir exudes pleasure and personality. The grapes come from a vineyard located at 400-metres above sea level. The harvest is manual; the spontaneous fermentation takes place with indigenous yeasts with maceration for a few days and ageing occurs for a few months in large barrels. Elegant and lovely with notes of strawberries, rhubarb and summer berries. Not unserious, but so so drinkable. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1rSaORV40T-MAhvfmy-6IxJgltVW2Y3aZ"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-11568 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1rSaORV40T-MAhvfmy-6IxJgltVW2Y3aZ" alt="" width="658" height="319" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1rSaORV40T-MAhvfmy-6IxJgltVW2Y3aZ 2163w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Louis-Aromatico-2024-300x146.jpg 300w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Louis-Aromatico-2024-1024x497.jpg 1024w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Louis-Aromatico-2024-768x373.jpg 768w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Louis-Aromatico-2024-1536x746.jpg 1536w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Louis-Aromatico-2024-2048x994.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 658px) 100vw, 658px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;2023 Louis Bianco Pinot Blanc/Chardonnay &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;2023 Louis Aromatico Gewurztraminer &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;2023 Louis Macerato Pinot Grigio &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;2022 Louis Rosso Pinot Noir &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;b&gt;Distillerie Cazottes, Southwest France&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The sweet taste of bitterness&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Vermouth has as many recipes as there are Italian families. Worse, it has made its mark on the Iberian Peninsula, where each &amp;#8220;vermuteria&amp;#8221; has its own. What were we going to enter into the competition, from the depths of the Tarn?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1bcSQvgV5RPacMTI1rbnZwsPMuW2V-NT_"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-5322 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1bcSQvgV5RPacMTI1rbnZwsPMuW2V-NT_" alt="" width="611" height="611" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1bcSQvgV5RPacMTI1rbnZwsPMuW2V-NT_ 1181w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/cazottes2-150x150.jpg 150w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/cazottes2-300x300.jpg 300w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/cazottes2-768x768.jpg 768w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/cazottes2-1024x1024.jpg 1024w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 611px) 100vw, 611px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;But yes! This bitter vermouth from none other than &lt;a href="https://www.distillerie-cazottes.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Laurent Cazottes&lt;/a&gt; is designed to be &amp;#8220;bitter&amp;#8221;, because it has to quench thirst, make one salivate, and reach for the bottle again. Gone is the sugar that cloys and clogs the palate: only 35g remains, for a &amp;#8220;dry&amp;#8221; impression and to enhance the strong aromatic. The bartender in one  will cry Martini, Manhattan, Rob Roy, Negroni! The vermouth is a true cocktail creature, but is of course perfectly enjoyed straight, on ice, with a dash of lemon zest thrown in, faux neglect oblige. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;This fortified wine incorporates Aubrac gentian roots, cinchona, cinnamon and liquorice bark, savoury flowers, caraway seeds, sage, tonka beans&amp;#8230; the result is a little bomb of aromatic bitterness (cue The Verve’s Bittersweet Symphony)!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The nose opens to the Orient, between ginger, camphor, and eucalyptus. Then we enter the old shaman&amp;#8217;s office, we run across the moors, we smell the blond leather of the horse&amp;#8217;s saddle, the fragrant tobacco, the wax and the heather honey. A stick of liquorice, a sloe picked at the edge of the fields, the chiffchaff crushed under the hoof, the smoke of the cade bush that fades after having warmed us&amp;#8230;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;A journey, yes, but also a skill: 24 months of ageing in old barrels, outdoors, subject to the vagaries of the weather. Then summer &amp;amp; autumn in a glass (or two).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1wI-rAwpH9AECKjo2IQAoa5YZvH9aIh9T"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-11570 aligncenter" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1wI-rAwpH9AECKjo2IQAoa5YZvH9aIh9T" alt="" width="164" height="547" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1wI-rAwpH9AECKjo2IQAoa5YZvH9aIh9T 180w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Cazottes-Bitter-Vermouth-producers-website-90x300.webp 90w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 164px) 100vw, 164px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;NV Bitter Vermouth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 style="text-align: center;"&gt;Interested in finding out more about the wines mentioned? Contact us directly:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;shop@lescaves.co.uk&lt;/strong&gt; |  &lt;strong&gt;sales@lescaves.co.uk&lt;/strong&gt; | 01483 538820&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
<wfw:commentRss>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/11/18/coming-soon-a-wine-list-near-you/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
</item>
<item>
<title>Wine Thoughts with Austrian producers Andert and Tscheppe</title>
<link>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/11/12/wine-thoughts-with-austrian-producers-andert-and-tscheppe/</link>
<comments>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/11/12/wine-thoughts-with-austrian-producers-andert-and-tscheppe/#respond</comments>
<dc:creator>blog</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 17:00:24 +0000</pubDate>
<category>Uncategorized</category>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/?p=11556</guid>
<description>“I hope your mind will explore the music and take you wherever the music takes you. It’s not a case of just singing along, it’s listening. It can be one note and that transports you somewhere. And I think if you can conjure up experiences and stories in your mind where the music takes you, [&amp;#8230;]</description>
<content:encoded>&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;“I hope your mind will explore the music and take you wherever the music takes you. It’s not a case of just singing along, it’s listening. It can be one note and that transports you somewhere. And I think if you can conjure up experiences and stories in your mind where the music takes you, to me that’s psychedelic. You have to listen to things, not just hear them.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&amp;#8211;John Lodge&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1XEFskXsTGvk0xN7-XUlPyTMbClVEoCYJ"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-11557" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1XEFskXsTGvk0xN7-XUlPyTMbClVEoCYJ" alt="" width="468" height="583" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1XEFskXsTGvk0xN7-XUlPyTMbClVEoCYJ 468w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/IMG_8876-241x300.jpg 241w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 468px) 100vw, 468px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Wine is life. Rather it is part of life, life being family and community and even the food that one grows and consumes, according to &lt;a href="https://www.andert-wein.at/en/"&gt;Michael Andert&lt;/a&gt; who I visited, along with his brother Eric, in Austria last month. Michael&amp;#8217;s definition of biodynamics is an equally all-embracing one, stating that it is natural for him to be natural (in the sense of understanding Nature and preserving her rhythms in his life and in his wines). And when you taste the wines, you understand they come from the particular person, their combined philosophy and actions, and finally the place itself &amp;#8211; a message reinforced by a visit to and stroll through the vineyard and garden at Lerchenfeld, sampling the bounty from the ground, the bushes, and plants. Tasting nature at first hand. Then you taste the wines and truly &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;feel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; where they come from.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Over the years, I have become less interested in the minutiae of wine production or forecasting what will be trendy next year, and more fixated on the actuality of the wine in the glass and how it makes me feel. I know less about wine than I used to, my professional detachment and scientific curiosity have diminished as my desire for simple (used advisedly) gratification increases. Like Michael Andert (and Andreas Tscheppe&amp;#8211;see below) I am comfortable in following my instincts. In my case, I would rather not be encumbered with detailed knowledge as I feel that gets in the way of my tasting empathetically.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;This is probably down to part laziness, part also the creeping realisation that for all the knowledge one may accrue about a wine – from digging into its vineyard origins to analysing its molecular make up – the major variable in any tasting experience is the human one. The fallible human, responsive to nuance one day, oblivious to it the next. The wine is thus not just what it is in a material sense, the object to be apprehended and evaluated for its quality &amp;#8211; it is also the diary of my shifting moods.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Maybe not knowing too much about the wine makes me feel that I am approaching the act of tasting it in a fresher state.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If I say that I don’t like a particular wine, it is probably because its flavours disconcert my momentary preference for (a certain kind of) balance. This is not an absolute judgement on the wine in question, more recognition that my personal taste increasingly dominates my professional judgement. Some wines you get, because they align with your particular taste sensibilities and needs at a given moment, others you can appreciate without loving. I would rather love than appreciate. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The fallible human, responsive to nuance one day, oblivious to it the next. The wine is thus not just what it is in a material sense &amp;#8211; the object to be apprehended and evaluated for its quality &amp;#8211; it is also the diary of my shifting moods.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Tastes can change.  I used to adore the aromas and flavours of decay in wines (earthy, mulchy, mushroominess), much as back then I preferred the warm russet colours of autumn, my favourite season. Now I favour the gush of the new vintage, the explosion of precocious fruit, minerals, energy and life, just as now I love the exuberance of spring.  If I can change my allegiance to the seasons, then surely I can change my wine preferences!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Tasting is also, of course, the right time meets the right environment and that helps to create the right (responsive) mood.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;With the Andert wines, I felt the nourishing aspect of a natural product made without anything added. Of liquid energy warming my body. Of completion. And to drink thoughtlessly, just like eating the raw veg dug from the soil or the berry plucked from a bush. Absolved from judging, one is momentarily restored to a state of uncultured appreciation.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1FLmEQqIC9W7txqYytPIjWN9tdpdlElN4"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-11558" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1FLmEQqIC9W7txqYytPIjWN9tdpdlElN4" alt="" width="468" height="582" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1FLmEQqIC9W7txqYytPIjWN9tdpdlElN4 468w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/IMG_8878-241x300.jpg 241w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 468px) 100vw, 468px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The next day, we visit &lt;a href="https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2018/06/13/doug-decants-the-wines-of-andreas-tscheppe/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Andreas Tscheppe&lt;/a&gt;. The wines are different, but similar emotions are engendered. When one tastes the wines, you sense the profound connection to a particular vineyard. You visit the vineyard, and you are looped back to the wine. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;When communicated, he passion of the growers is key to an enhanced experience. They are not trying to impress you or forcing their opinions on you but simply describing what they think and do. For Michael, his love for the vineyard and the garden is primal. And there is a deep respect too. Andreas is the vibrating human link in the chain, theorising, tinkering, inventing, experimenting and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;doing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;. This dancing energy is evident in the fabric of his wines.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1LW-f3SPHjpQKcLXHKhJTUyxFo-8r8i3n"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter  wp-image-11559" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1LW-f3SPHjpQKcLXHKhJTUyxFo-8r8i3n" alt="" width="480" height="596" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1LW-f3SPHjpQKcLXHKhJTUyxFo-8r8i3n 468w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/IMG_8879-242x300.jpg 242w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 480px) 100vw, 480px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;This reminds me of Goethe’s Faust, wherein Faust is translating the famous passage from The Gospel According to John.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;‘Tis written: “In the beginning was the Word!”&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Here now I&amp;#8217;m balked! Who&amp;#8217;ll put me in accord?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;It is impossible, the Word so high to prize,&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;I must translate it otherwise&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If I am rightly by the Spirit taught.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&amp;#8216;Tis written: In the beginning was the Thought!&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Consider well that line, the first you see,&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;That your pen may not write too hastily!&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Is it then Thought that works, creative, hour by hour?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Thus should it stand: In the beginning was the Power!&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Yet even while I write this word, I falter,&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;For something warns me, this too I shall alter.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The Spirit&amp;#8217;s helping me! I see now what I need&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;And write assured: In the beginning was the Deed!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;For Andreas (and Michael) the wines are as by-products of their happy existence in Nature, as well as liquid proof of the relationship they enjoy with their vineyards. Tasting and drinking the wines &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;in situ&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; is to be briefly admitted to the family and to be part of the conversations they are having with their environment.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1kyYNK7nWpYCMRkmjJjmlUSNbFHW-NCy7"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter  wp-image-8852" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1kyYNK7nWpYCMRkmjJjmlUSNbFHW-NCy7" alt="" width="479" height="488" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1kyYNK7nWpYCMRkmjJjmlUSNbFHW-NCy7 741w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/IMG_2447-294x300.jpg 294w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 479px) 100vw, 479px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1lSexoPLAPNPrHLiMojgn2debGx5t-YiP"&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter  wp-image-8851" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1lSexoPLAPNPrHLiMojgn2debGx5t-YiP" alt="" width="479" height="493" srcset="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;id=1lSexoPLAPNPrHLiMojgn2debGx5t-YiP 750w, https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/IMG_2442-291x300.jpg 291w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 479px) 100vw, 479px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interested in finding more about the wines of Andert and Tscheppe? Contact us directly:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:shop@lescaves.co.uk"&gt;shop@lescaves.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; |  &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:sales@lescaves.co.uk"&gt;sales@lescaves.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; | 01483 538820&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
<wfw:commentRss>https://blog.lescaves.co.uk/2025/11/12/wine-thoughts-with-austrian-producers-andert-and-tscheppe/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>